<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe discourse of two most cruell and bloudie murthers, committed bothe in Worcestershire, and bothe happening vnhappily in the yeare 1583 The first declaring, how one unnaturally murdered his neighbour, and afterward buried him in his seller. The other sheweth, how a woman unlawfully following the deuillish lusts of the flesh with her seruant, caused him very cruelly to kill her owne husband.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1583</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839394</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839394</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3809</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15706)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3809)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1264:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe discourse of two most cruell and bloudie murthers, committed bothe in Worcestershire, and bothe happening vnhappily in the yeare 1583 The first declaring, how one unnaturally murdered his neighbour, and afterward buried him in his seller. The other sheweth, how a woman unlawfully following the deuillish lusts of the flesh with her seruant, caused him very cruelly to kill her owne husband.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Roger Warde, dwelling neere Holbourne Conduit at the signe of the Talbot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1583.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A discourse of two cruell murders.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: AB⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Murder --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3809:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3809:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A BRIEFE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVRSE OF TWO moſt cruell and bloudie murthers, committed bothe in <hi>Worcesterſhire,</hi> and bothe happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>vnhappily in the yeare. 1583.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt declaring, how <hi>one vnnaturally murdered his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and afterward buried him in his Seller.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other ſheweth, how <hi>a woman vnlawfully following the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilliſh luſts of the fleſh with her ſeruant, cauſed him very cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to kill her owne Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at <hi>London.</hi> by <hi>Roger Warde,</hi> dwelling neere <hi>Holburne Conduit</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Talbot.</hi> 1583.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3809:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3809:2"/>
            <head>To the reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the dayes of daunger and iniquitie are as now, not onelie our own fraile nature maye ſufficiently certefie vs: but alſo the irk<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſome examples, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted prodigious ſpectacles, euery day and houre (almoſt) apparant in our eies, may driue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs anye doubt to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. For if we enter into examination with our ſelues, aſwell of our negligence of duetie to our God, as alſo our lacke of looue to our neighbour: wee ſhall finde that we are not, neither doo as the holie Euangeliſt wiſheth vs, when he ſaith:<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, let vs looue one an other, for loue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of God, and euerie one that looueth, is borne of God, and knoweth God: But he that loueth not, knoweth not God, for God is Loue.</hi> And I find in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> theſe words.
<pb facs="tcp:3809:3"/>
               <hi>Three thinges reioyce me, and by them am I beautified before God and men:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 25.1.</note> 
               <hi>the vnitie of Brethren, the looue of neighboures, &amp; a man and wife that agree together.</hi> Howe then can we otherwiſe iudge, but that we are in that yron and crooked age, wherein iniquitie ſhould vaunt &amp; ſhew her ſelfe: beeing made acquainted euery day with the lack of that heauenly orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, Loue, the memory thereof almoſt defaced and puld vp by the roote, in ſo greeuous and vehement manner, that it may be hardly ſayde to haue anie abiding amonge vs at all. And that I may not wade into abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of matter, without due proofe to affirme anye thinge alleadged: I praye you looke into theſe Tragicall accidents following, whiche, albeit they carrye terrour ſufficient, to forwarne the vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall children of this worlde: yet daylie doo freſh enormities ſpring vp, able (had nature ſo agreed) to vrge the verie bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elles of the earth, to yeelde foorth feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acclamations agaynſt vs. Shall I with-hold to ſay, that the father hath not procured the death of his owne naturall
<pb facs="tcp:3809:3"/>childe: and the childe riſen in like occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion agaynſt his Father? Shall I not ſaye, the Huſband hath abrydged the lyfe of his eſpouſed Wife and mate, &amp; ſhe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe committed the like vnnaturall acte on her Huſband? Hath not one Brother murdered the other, one neighbour kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the other, one frend been falſe to the other, yea, &amp; very nature turned agaynſt it ſelf? Theſe vnlooked for examples are daily before vs, ſo that wee cannot ſhun the ſight &amp; hearing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; yet ſhal we paſſe them ouer with a ſlender or lighte regarde? Oh my freends, doo we not ſee the heauens frowne? And why? Becauſe the ſinnes of the earth hath fumed vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the noſethrils of the Almightie, with a ſauour ſo yrkſome &amp; vnſufferable: that he cannot in Iuſtice, but ſtrike ſtiff-nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Pharao,</hi> with the rodde of his furie, yea, and bereaue the earth of thoſe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolent bleſſinges, which he hath ſuffered it ſo quietly to enioye, and ſo great abuſe rendered vnto him for them. Can wee reprooue the Father for diſinheriting his Sonne, when hee ſeeeth his dealynges
<pb facs="tcp:3809:4"/>ſuch as deſerueth nothing? can we blame that maiſter, who thruſteth his ſeruaunt foorth of his doores, when he beholdeth his behauiour vnworthy of houſe-room? Euen ſo, can wee otherwiſe ſay, that our heauenly father dooth vnworthily caſt vs out of his fauour, when in ſteade of looue, we render him hatred, for dutie, negligence, and for all his good gifts, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratious thanks? Oh no, let vs not enter into ſuche queſtioning with our ſelues, for if we looke into our iniquitie, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into his mercie, our daily falling from one ſinne into an other, and his ſo long fatherly forbearance: we wil then quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie returne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fleſh pots of Aegypt, and from our owne filthie and odious vomit, and euerie one of vs ſay hartelie with the Pſalmiſt:<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.3.</note> 
               <hi>I do knowe mine owne wickednes, and my ſinne is euer againſt me.</hi> And likewiſe confeſſe with <hi>Danyel</hi> the Prophet:<note place="margin">Daniel 9.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>To thee (O Lord God) belongeth mercie and forgiuenes, for wee haue gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from thee, and haue not harkened to thy voyce, wherby we might walke in thy lawes which thou hast appointed for vs.</hi> It is high
<pb facs="tcp:3809:4"/>time that we ſhould thus conſider with our ſelues, if wee but looke into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſions offered vnto vs, and mark how buſie the deuil is to woork ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ouerthrow: the rather by 2. greeuous &amp; horrible miſchances which hath late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happened, wherin may be ſeene, how needefull it is for vs to call for the grace of our heauenly father, to ſtrengthen vs with ſuch aſſured confidence, that we fall not likewiſe into ſuch euil, but may ſhew ſuch hartie repentance of our former offences, as the verie wicked by our good example, maye bee drawne to glorify the eternall GOD.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account_of_a_murder">
            <pb facs="tcp:3809:5"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A moſt cruel and bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Murder, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted on</hi> New-yeares euen</hi> laſt paſt, beeing the laſt day of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> 1582. in the town of <hi>Eſam</hi> in <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> ſhire, by one <hi>Thomas Smith</hi> a town dweller, vpon his neighbor <hi>Robert Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noll,</hi> who when he had cruelly murdered him, made a graue in his Seller, &amp; there buried him.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N <hi>Eſam,</hi> a hanſome mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ket Town in <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſhire well known, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led two youngmen, who by their vſual trade were Mercers, as in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> country they call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſell all kind of wares: the one of them they called <hi>Robert Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noll,</hi> a bacheler, &amp; of ſuch an honeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as he was not onely wel beloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Towne where he dwelt, but alſo of thoſe who had euerie market day acceſſe thither, for their néedfull neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was as wel cuſtomed as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occupier in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne. The other was called <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> of indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t welth likewiſe, &amp; ſon to one of the moſt ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne, &amp; ioyned in mariage
<pb facs="tcp:3809:5"/>with a gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of very good paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he likewiſe was well thought on of moſt &amp; leaſt. This <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> ſéeing <hi>Greenoll</hi> haue ſo good vtteraunce for his wares, and ſo well eſtéemed in ech companierif not vppon this cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, though chiefly it bee accounted ſo, he began to enuy the proſperous eſtate of him béeing his neighbour and frend, and the Deuill ſo farre ruled the courſe of his enuious intent, as nothing wold ſuffiſe the deſire thereof, but onely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of <hi>Greenoll</hi> by death, which though hee had no reaſon for, yet ſuche was the perſwaſion of the euill ſpirite with him. Manie platformes were laid, a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d deuiſes canuazed ouer by this lewde man, which way he might woork the death of his frendly neighbor: at laſt as the Deuill wanteth no occaſions to helpe man forward to his own deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo he preſented <hi>Smith</hi> with a fit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, whereby he might execute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſum of his bloody will. And as the repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at our neighbors proſperity, is not onely monſtrous, but a deniliſh nature.
<pb facs="tcp:3809:6"/>So had this man compaſſed a monſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and moſte deuiliſh deuiſe, the verie conceite whereof is able to aſtoniſh the heart of a Iewe, or Mahomitans recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, and thus it was as followeth.</p>
            <p>On <hi>New-yeares euen</hi> laſte paſt, this <hi>Thomas Smith</hi> longinge and deſiringe the end of his vnnaturall will, bearing the image of a frendlie countenaunce in the face, but the verie perfecte ſhape of <hi>Iudas</hi> tretcherie in his hart, inuited his neighbour <hi>Greenoll</hi> to his houſe, where he promiſed to beſtowe a quart of wine and an apple vpon him: ſaying further, they woulde paſſe awaye the Euening pleaſauntly in frendlie talke and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king together. <hi>Greenoll</hi> béeing one deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of eche mans frendſhip, and much the rather of his béeing his neighbour, and one of the ſame trade himſelf was: nothing miſtruſting the villanous trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hyd vnder ſo ſmooth a ſhow of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berhood, gaue him thanks, promiſing to come to him at night, &amp; not to faile him. This pleaſed well the bloud-thirſting man, ſo that home he we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to determine
<pb facs="tcp:3809:6"/>the Inſtrument to doo the déede withal, &amp; then downe into his Seller hee goes, to diſpoſe a place wherein he might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uay the bodie when hee had ſlayne him: there he digged a graue about ſixe or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ynches déepe, thinking there to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie him that he ſhould neuer be founde. It drew toward night, when as a play was cryed about the Towne, whereto both old and young did haſtely repaire: &amp; this <hi>Smith</hi> hauing a boye that ſerued him in his Shop, fearing leaſte the boye ſhoulde perceiue anie thinge, gaue hym money, and bad him goe fée the Play: &amp; bring him the whole report of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This he did in the preſence of <hi>Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nol,</hi> who was come according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſe to kéepe him companie: &amp; the boye hauing fetcht a quarte of wine and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as his maiſter willed him, ran me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to ſée the Play, leauing <hi>Greenoll</hi> &amp; his maiſter by the fire pleaſauntly tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. They twoo thus ſitting alone, did drinke to ech other verie familiarly, tyll at laſt, <hi>Greenol</hi> ſtouping to turne an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the fire, a fit time that <hi>Smith</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied
<pb facs="tcp:3809:7"/>to accompliſh his will: who taking an yron peſtell, wherewith hee vſed to beate his ſpice in the morter, and which he had laid by him ready for the nonce, with this peſtel (as <hi>Greenoll</hi> ſtouped to turne the Apple) he gaue him twoo ſuche mightie blowes on the heade, as hée fell down backward to the ground, yéelding foorth a verie pittifull and lamentable groane. <hi>Smith</hi> hearing him to giue ſuch a woful groane (as himſelfe ſaid to me, when I came to him into the priſon) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to enter into ſome ſorrowfulnes for the déede, wiſhinge that hee mighte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer againe: but when he perceiued he had ſmote him ſo ſore, that ther was no hope of his recouerie, he tooke the peſtel againe, and gaue him thrée or four more cruell ſtrokes about the heade, whiche made him to lie trembling and ſhaking in ſuch pittifull manner, as would haue made a hearte of Adamant to melte in griefe: for to beholde how life and death made ſtrife together, life for the ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to reſiſt death his bitternes, wyth many a gaſpe for breath, with ſtrugling
<pb facs="tcp:3809:7"/>and often folding his armes together: thus laye this Innocent and martyred coarſe. Not ſuffiſed with this, the bloody murderer taketh a knife, and therewith cut the throate of <hi>Greenol,</hi> but as <hi>Smith</hi> himſelfe ſaith, he did not cut the weza<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but pierced the ſkin ſomwhat: and then would haue ſtabbed him to the heart w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the knife, but miſſed and ſmote him on the ſhoulder blade, whervpon he ſtrooke againe, and then indéede pierced him to the heart: what a cruell and monſtrous harde heart had hee, that coulde endure this rufull Stratageme? When hée had ſuffiſed his bloody mind, vpon his fréend and loouing neighbour, hee drewe him down into his Seller, where his graue was readie prepared for him, and there buried him: which béeing doone, he ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed it ouer ſo finelye with a Trowell that Playſterers vſe, ſo that it could be hardly diſcerned, and becauſe he would woorke the ſurer, hee tooke Bayles of Flax which laye in his Seller, and ſo ſhaked the ſhellinges thereof on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floore in all places, as no one coulde ſaye,
<pb facs="tcp:3809:8"/>(but he that knewe it) where the graue was, ſetting likewiſe Drifats &amp; Cheſts ouer it, ſo that he iudged it ſhould neuer be found. Afterward he went and tooke water, wherewith he waſhed and dryed his houſe ſo clean in euerie place, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one drop of blood could not be eſpied: behold howe ſubtilly hee wente to woorke, but God, who in no caſe will haue bloudie murder hidde, preuented all his craitie pollicies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Smith</hi> hauing thus plaide his tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous pageant, &amp; hauing taken <hi>Greenols</hi> keyes of his ſhop from him, wente thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and likewiſe robbed it, bringing a great deale of the goods from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>re into his owne houſe. But this by the way is to bee conſidered, that in the Towne of <hi>Eueſam,</hi> all the time of <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> and at no other time, there is watch &amp; ward kept, that no miſorder or il rule be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the Towne, which doubtleſſe is a verie good and commendable order. To one of the watchmen had <hi>Smith</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen this watch-woord, <hi>See and ſee not:</hi> which was onelie to this ende, that hee
<pb facs="tcp:3809:8"/>might goe by them vnſéene, when he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed the goods out of <hi>Greenols</hi> ſhop to his owne houſe. On the morrowe when it was knowen that <hi>Greenols</hi> ſhop was robde, queſtion was made thorowe the Towne, who was abroade that nighte that might bee ſuſpected, becauſe of the Playe that was in the Towne: vppon which demaund, the watchman to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this meſſage was ſente, declared howe <hi>Thomas Smith</hi> was abroad ſomewhat late, and ſent him this watch-word, <hi>See and ſee not,</hi> but was meant thereby hée could not gather. Vpon this, <hi>Smith</hi> was ſent for before the chiefe of the Towne, and demaunded if he knew where <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nol</hi> was, for that it was reported he had béene in his houſe ouer-night, and ſince that time no man could tell anie tidin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of him: moreouer his ſhop was rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed as that night, and that <hi>Smith</hi> béeing abroad, and ſending ſuch a by-woord <hi>See and ſee not,</hi> to one of the watchmen, yt was a ſhrewd preſumption againſt him to bee ſomewhat faultie in the matter. So after his aunſwere, that hee knewe
<pb facs="tcp:3809:9"/>not where <hi>Greenol</hi> was become, and by his late walkinge and woordes ſente to the watchman, no harme was meante: they ſaid that they would goe to ſearche his houſe, whervpon <hi>Smith</hi> aunſwered, that his houſe they could not as then ſée. becauſe his wife was at <hi>Kinges Norto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> a Towne not farre thence, and ſhe had the keyes of his houſe: but (quoth hee) if you will ſearch my Seller you maye, and ſo tooke the keyes from his girdle and threw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto them. Then went certayne that were appointed, to ſearch <hi>Smiths</hi> Seller, whence they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming again without finding ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as they looked for: till by chaunce one of them happened to eſpye a little péece of earth, as it were new broken out of the grounde, lying vnder the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermoſte ſtaire, which he taking vp, ſaid it were good to ſée where any earth was latelye broken there about, for if they chaunced to finde the place, ſome thing might come to light woorth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding. Vpon this councel they began all to looke earneſtlye about the Seller,
<pb facs="tcp:3809:9"/>if they could finde the place where that Earth had béene broken vp. At laſt they remooued the Cheſts &amp; Dryfats, where they felt the ground more ſoft then all the reſt: which cauſed them (ſuſpecting ſomewhat) to fall to digging, where preſently they found <hi>Greenoll</hi> buryed, not paſt ſix or ſeuen inches déepe, and looking vppon him, beheld how cruelly and vnnaturally he had beene murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Theſe newes brought to the Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifs of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne, where <hi>Smith</hi> was kept till they returned: not without great lamentation for this bloody déed, of all that knew or heard thereof, he was ſent to <hi>Worceſter</hi> Gaole, wher he remained till ſuch time as the crueltie of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neighbour like déede might be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Iuſtice. When y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aſſiſes came, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apparaunt truth of his offence layd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Iudges, he was condemned to the death, which he ſuffered very lately ſince: but yet by the earneſt intreatie of his Fréendes, who were of great wealth and credit, the ſeueritie of the lawe was not altogether miniſtred, for
<pb facs="tcp:3809:10"/>wheras he ſhould haue béene hanged in chains, he had more fauour ſhewd him, he was hanged to death, and after ward buryed.</p>
            <p>Thus my Fréendes, haue you heard the true diſcourſe of this moſt bloody &amp; monſtrous act, accordinge as in great greefe, with like ſorowe for the deed, him ſelfe dyd vtter it, both vnto me, and diners other being preſent, Preachers, and Gentlemen. And truly thus much I muſt ſay, for the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truely he was both a hanſome and well featured a Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as one ſhall lightly ſoe, his Father aſ good wealth, and one of the chiefs in the Towne of <hi>Eſam,</hi> and hee had béene marryed not paſt eight wéeks by crrbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reporte, before he did the deed, to a Gentls woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of very good Parentage, who no donbt remaineth in great gréef for this vnlooked for miſchaunce, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing merty abroade with her: Freends, when her Haſoand at home conunitted this cruell deed: I commit it to the Iudgement of all verfuous Women, what a groefe it was to her, when firſt
<pb facs="tcp:3809:10"/>ſhe heard of theſe vnhappy newes: But héere I may not make a final pauſe, for that an other horrible and wicked déed, committed in <hi>Iune</hi> laſt <hi>1582.</hi> in the ſame Sheire, conſtraineth me to ſpeak ſomewhat thereof: and for that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the death of one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partyes, I am the more willing to paſſe it ouer in a bréefe diſcourſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account_of_a_murder">
            <head>An other moſt cruel and bloody Murder, committed in the ſame ſhire the ſame yeere as the afore-ſaid.</head>
            <p>AT a place called <hi>Cothridge,</hi> about four myles diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Worceſter,</hi> dwelt an honeſt Hubſband-ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, named <hi>Thomas Beaſt,</hi> one very well reputed among his Neighbours, aſwell for his houſe keeping, as alſo for his Godly and honeſt behauiour. This afore named <hi>Thomas Beaſt,</hi> kept a hanſome Yong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to his ſeruant, called <hi>Chriſtopher Tomſon,</hi> to whome (by the wicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation
<pb facs="tcp:3809:11"/>and prouocation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Deuill) the good Wife of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe vſed far better affection, then to her owne Huſband.</p>
            <p>Often times they would carnally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues together, till luſt had gotten ſo much power of the Woman: as ſhe began altogether to loathe and diſlike her Huſband, and preferre the fleſhly dealings of her new companion ſo much, as ſhe muſt néeds ſéeke &amp; prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe the death of her Huſband.</p>
            <p>The Neighbours not ſuſpecting, but credibly perceiuing, the common and vnhoneſt behauiour of this wicked wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man &amp; her luſty Yonker: began ſo much to diſlike thereof, as if came at laſt to her Huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds eares, who as wel to ſlake the rumor of the Prople, as alſo the pleaſure theſe two vnhoneſtly enioied: gaue his Seruaunt warning to anoyd his howſe, who packed vp his clothes, and was departing: But that this fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie deſirous Woman, ſo much preuay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the matter with her Huſband. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her Companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> departed not, but taryed ſtill. At length, ſo great grew the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tréd
<pb facs="tcp:3809:11"/>of this harlot againſt her Huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, as ſhe muſt néeds haue <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> her ſweet dallying Fréend, to diſpatch the life of him, wherto a great while he would not conſent, perſwading her ſtil from it; ſo much as in him lay. But it grew to ſuch an iſſue at the laſt, as ſhe muſt néeds haue her will, and <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher</hi> muſt not deny her thereof, for ſhe coniured him by the looue that he bare her, and if any way he would witneſſe his affection vnto her, to manifeſt it in the killing her Huſband, for (quoth ſhe) with mony and fréends I will warrant thée to ſaue thy life, and then thou and I will liue merrily together. Oh moſt horrible and wicked Womon, a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nay a deuill: ſtop your eares you chaſte &amp; graue matrones, whome Gods feare, dutie, true looue to your Huſbands, and vertue of your ſelues hath ſo beautified as nothing ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be more odious vnto you, then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch a graceleſſe ſtrumpet ſhould be found, ſo much to diſhonor your no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſexe. Well, when neither intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faire meanes <hi>Chriſtopher</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3809:12"/>could vſe, to ſubuert this deuiliſh deſire: ſollemnely at the eating of a Poſſet, the night before he did the deede, he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her faithfully, to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh her will. On y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morrowe when his Maiſter was in his feeld at the plow, he takes a long pike ſtaffe on his necke, wherwith he would goe doo the deed: but his wicked Miſtreſſe miſſiking the weapon, ſaying that it was nothing fit for the purpoſe, deliuered him a Forreſt Bil, which ſhe her ſelf had made very ſharp for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame infent, and ſaid: Be ſure to hit him right, and thou ſhalt ſpeed him I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant thée, ſo that he ſhal neuer tell who did hurt him. <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> taketh this Bil on his back, &amp; comes into the feeld to his Maiſter, where he began quarre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to ſay vnto him after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Seeing you are willing I ſhall ſerue you no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, giue me that which is my dutie &amp; ſo fare ye wel, with other woords of quarrell that he vſed about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſum of the mony, but his Maiſter grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him ſo much as he demaunded, and turning from him, to open his purſſe to
<pb facs="tcp:3809:12"/>giue him the mony, <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> ſtrooke at him with the Bil in ſuch cruel man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there he killed him. After the déed was done, he fled, but not farre before he was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when preſently he exclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on his Miſtres, how ſhe was cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted the deed: wherupon they were both ſent to <hi>Worceſter</hi> Gaole, where very often ſhee would ſollicite her ſwéet <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> with mony, hand kerchers, noſegaies, and ſuch like amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and loouing tokens, and he beſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his naughtie affection, would ſhape all his conditions to pleaſe her, the more to witnes his diſſolute folly, he made a triumphe (as it were) in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying a locke of her haire about him, &amp; would ſit kiſſing and delighting in any token ſhe ſent him: beſyde, one day he deſired the Iaylor, that if he were a Man, or one that regarded the extreme afflictions of thoſe, whom the tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny of looue poſſeſſed, that he wold doo ſo much for him, to rip foorth the hart of him, &amp; cleauing the ſame in ſunder, he ſhould there beholde the liuely Image of his
<pb facs="tcp:3809:13"/>ſwéet miſtreſſe, to whom (as the théefeſt Iewell he had) hee deſtred him to make a preſent of that pretions token.</p>
            <p>When time came, that Iuſtice ſhould determine of theſe twaine, béeing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily found guiltie and condemned: ſhee was adiudged (for an example to all lighte and laſciuious women) that ſhee ſhould bee burned, &amp; <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> to bée carried to the place where he did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> déed: there to be firſt ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grd dead, &amp; afterward to be hanged vp againe in chaines. The Aſſiſes béeing holden at <hi>Eſam,</hi> ſhee was laide vpon an hurdle, &amp; ſo drawne to the place of Execution, which was without the lown: &amp; there béeing bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtake, &amp; the fire made to burne about her, her wertched carkas was ſoone diſſolued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to athes. <hi>Chriſtopher Tomſon,</hi> he was carried back again to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> where he likewiſe (for an example to all lewd liuers) was drawne on an hurdle about the Eittie, &amp; ſo conuayed to <hi>Cothridge,</hi> where according to his iudgment he hangeth in chaynes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3809:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
